<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A resolution of this case, viz. Whether it be lawful to separate from the publick worship of God in the parochial assemblies of England, upon that new pretence, which some men make, of the case being much altered now from what it was, when the Puritans wrote against the Brownists and the Presbyterians against the Independent</title>
            <author>Francklin, John, d. 1689.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 102 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40398</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12724895</idno>
  <idno type="VID">66320</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240950202</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2081</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16565</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12724895</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40398)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66320)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 693:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A resolution of this case, viz. Whether it be lawful to separate from the publick worship of God in the parochial assemblies of England, upon that new pretence, which some men make, of the case being much altered now from what it was, when the Puritans wrote against the Brownists and the Presbyterians against the Independent</title>
                  <author>Francklin, John, d. 1689.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>47 [i.e. 55] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A. Grover, for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Francklin.  Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.)</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Church of England --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:66320:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:66320:1"/>
            <p>A RESOLUTION OF THIS CASE, <hi>VIZ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether it be Lawful to separate from the Publick Worship of God in the <hi>PAROCHIAL Assemblies</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> upon that New Pretence, which some Men make, Of the Case being much Altered now from what it was, when the <hi>Puritans</hi> wrote against the <hi>Brownists</hi> and the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> against the <hi>Independent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. Grover,</hi> for <hi>Walter Kettilby</hi> at the <hi>Bishop's-Head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1683.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="objections">
            <pb facs="tcp:66320:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:66320:2"/>
            <head>The more Modern Objections, which are now pretended by our <hi>Dissenters,</hi> to alter the Case, are these which follow; being Particularly answer'd, (mostly out of the <hi>Nonconforming Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters</hi> own Writings) in these Papers.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1. IT look's more like compliance with Carnal Interest than Conscience, for Men to hold Communion with Parish-Assemblies at this time.</item>
               <item>2. There are many more Corruptions and Impositions in the Church now, which hinder our Communion with it.</item>
               <item>3. I could go to the Publick Assemblies if I were left to my own Liberty of Conscience, but I cannot do it being Compell'd.</item>
               <item>4. We have now more Experience and Light than was formerly, to direct us.</item>
               <item>5. If we should now join in Communion with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> we should seem guilty of <hi>Apostacy,</hi> in build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the things we our selves once destroyed.</item>
               <item>6. We are entered now into a Solemn League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to endeavour greater Reformation in the Church.</item>
               <item>7. If I comply with the Liturgy at this Time, I should gratifie the <hi>Papists,</hi> and weaken the <hi>Protestant</hi> Interest.</item>
               <item>8. I cannot hold Communion with Railers and Perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors, and such Scandalous Persons, as are most, Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters and People in the Publick Assemblies now adays▪</item>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:66320:3"/>
               <item>9. The way of Preaching is now quite altered, and the Doctrines that are generally taught are very corrupt; either meer Morality or else thorow-paced <hi>Arminianism</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>10. Our <hi>Nonconforming</hi> Ministers themselves (who doubtless well know what they do) will not go to Church now, whereas formerly they did.</item>
               <item>11. If we should not attend the Ministry of the <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformists</hi> still, They must starve for want of Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, they being Poor and Indigent, having lost their Livings.</item>
               <item>12. There have been so many Books written of late in Defence of <hi>Nonconformity,</hi> that I cannot be satisfy'd, but still remain in Doubt, Whether it be lawful to hold Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the <hi>Parochial Assemblies:</hi> I vehemently suspect it to be sinful, and <hi>whatsoever is not of Faith is Sin,</hi> and therefore there's an end of the Controversy.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:66320:3"/>
            <head>A RESOLUTION OF THIS CASE, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>PEACE and Unity, as they are the great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign of the <hi>Christian Doctrine,</hi> so is the want of them no where more fatal, and more to be lamented than in the <hi>Christian Church.</hi> Our later Ages have sufficiently demonstrated the sad effects of our Dissentions; I wish the sense of them might unite all Christians; but especially such of us, as se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate upon <hi>small pretences,</hi> if not <hi>less Reason.</hi> For 'tis Pitty that any [little] matter should be the occasion of so great an Evil amongst such. 'Tis enough sad, that <hi>Protestants</hi> (after all their peaceable Endeavours) cannot gain <hi>Ʋnity</hi> with others: 'Tis too much so, that any Breach should be maintain'd and widen'd among themselves. Here, Friends ought not sure to fall out with, and separate from one another upon light occasions; which, to be sure, can effectually advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage none but their Enemies, and afflict none more than themselves.</p>
            <p>The sence of this hath, not only here of late forc't many seasonable Persuasives from several of our Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent <hi>London-Ministers of the Church of</hi> England, (in those excellent <hi>Resolutions of</hi> many <hi>Cases of Conscience</hi>)
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:66320:4"/> tending to Unite us; but likewise hath ever rendred separation from the Publick Worship of God in the <hi>Parochial</hi> Assemblies, so unbeseeming, so unnatural even to the Old Nonconforming Divines themselves, That there is nothing can be more evident to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent part of Mankind who have read Men and Books, than that themselves have Writ strenuously a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst it (as hath been sufficiently already shew'n in that late excellent Piece, called, <hi>The Case of Lay-Communion, justified from the Testimony of above an hundred</hi> Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formists) and in their own Writings have answered all the Objections that are usually made. And therefore our present Separatists, to vindicate themselves in this Point, and that they may not be thought Apostates from their Principles, have endeavoured to find out a vast Difference between the state of the Parish Churches now, and what they were in those days.</p>
            <p>The Design of this Paper is (with the greatest Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour and Charity) to help them likewise off this Rock, against which they seem so willing to Ship-wrack the Peace and Unity of the Church, and to consider those Differences which are pretended, and to answer them (for their stronger Convincement) mostly out of their own Writings (not medling with any that have been collected into that late Piece above-named) against that <hi>New Sett of Objections,</hi> lately started up; when the old one's like so many lying Oracles are struck Dumb by the force of Ancient and Modern Arguments of those several eminent <hi>Divines in</hi> London.</p>
            <p>First of all, <hi>They now Object and tell us, That it looks</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>1</label>
               <hi>more like Compliance with Carnal Interest than Conscience for Men to hold Communion with Parish-Assemblies at this time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Objection than which none is more common (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>
               </label> the Vulgar of them especially) when Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:66320:4"/> is urged. But why must a Regular Obedience to Laws be called a Compliance with Carnal Interest? Why may it not be more Charitably presumed that the Reason why some Men alter their former Principles and Practices, is, because they have now taken more pains than ordinary in studying, reading, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coursing the Point of <hi>Lay-Communion,</hi> and so discover themselves to have been in the wrong all this while, having been imposed upon by the subtle Insinuations of their Guides, whose wrested Interpretations of Scripture and Misapplications of Texts have led them into Paths of Separation in order to the promoting a Private Interest. No one Principle hath proved a greater friend to Separation than Men's Pride, in thinking it a Disgrace to change their Minds tho' up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the clearest Convictions and most apparent Reason. Hath it not been the practice of the Wisest Men that ever were, to alter their Judgments upon more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and solid thoughts? Must a Man always be of this Mind because he once was so? St. <hi>Austin</hi> himself wrote his Retractions. Days teach Knowledge, and every Man is, or ought to be, Wiser as he is Older, and more experienced. We ought not, therefore, to censure any Man, as guided by Carnal Interest, when he can give a better Reason for his Action in attending the Publick Worship of God in the <hi>Parochial Assemblies,</hi> than we who Censure him can give against it; and perhaps he hath taken ten times the pains rightly to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form his Understanding, than one that scruples it hath done. So that what one Man may think a Sin to do, he may think it a Sin to forbear. The uncharitable Censorious Person hath lost half the Religion of a Christian; and hath exchanged one of the fairest Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of a Saint, for one of the Blackest Characters of a Devil.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:66320:5"/>
            <p>By the same Rule that I censure another Man for differing from me, he may censure me for differing from him; and then if Almighty God should Damn us all, for such things which straight-laced, narrow-soul'd Christians Damn one another for, very few would be saved. It's better to give an account to a Merciful God for too much Charity, than for too great Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soriousness.</p>
            <p>The Reverend Mr. <hi>How</hi> methinks (would they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider him) hath spoken enough to convince them of this fault, and to answer this their Objection, <hi>in his Sermon at the Morning Exercise, in that last Volume lately published.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>This Objection (says he) smells strong in a very high Degree of Uncharitableness, very unbecoming a true Christian temper; which would make us ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stain from Censuring of one another as Insincere, upon the account of Religious Differences. Where Love remains and bears rule, it cannot be that they, who are unsatisfied with the way of Worship that Generally obtains, should censure them that are satisfied, as if they were Insincere, meerly because of this Difference.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Why should we think that nothing but corrupt Inclinations must govern some Christians, who think it their Duty to attend the Publick Forms, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to testify their Union with other sincere Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians under those Forms, especially in a time when the Contest is so high in the World, between them who prosess the Substance of reformed Christianity, and them that have so much deformed it? Why may not some Christians think it becomes them at any time to express their Unconfinedness to a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and to use that Christian Liberty, which they think should not be judged by another Man's Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:66320:5"/> which yet they would have regard unto, were there not greater reasons to preponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate?</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>True Christian Love, and Compassion of Humane frailty, and an humble sence of a man's own weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness should oblige him to think, that Conscience towards God may have a greater Hand in guiding Men the different ways they take, than is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thought. We ought to consider that tho' such and such reasons seem not weighty to us, they may to some others, who are as much affraid of sinning against God as we; and perhaps their Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstandings are as good in other matters as ours. Men's Apprehensions are of a different size, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently their Consciencious Determinations: And they have various relishes of things which we ought to consider with Equanimity to make us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>srain hard Censures. The Martyrs in Queen <hi>Mary's</hi> Days found great Spiritual refreshing by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer: And so some in our Days profess that their Hearts have been much warmed, and their Affections rais'd by it. It would be uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable, more to suspect their sincerity than our own. It's a difficult thing to sit in Judgment up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on another Man; especially in a matter of so high a nature as the Posture of his heart towards God. If some have more Latitude than I, and think what they may do in present Circumstances; so far as they may, they must. Would it not be the Dictate of Love, patiently to admit it, especially when it comes to suffering? Thus he.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And what can be more close, then such reasoning, to their Objection? And not much behind him is <hi>Mr. Gifford,</hi> the old <hi>Nonconformist,</hi> who was so far from looking upon Communion with the Church,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:66320:6"/> as a meer compliance with Carnal Interest, that he tells you <q>Some Separatists are proceeded so far, that they will not hear the Prayers of the Book; which I take to be a greater Sin than many do suppose. Nay, says he, some are gone so far as to fall into a Damnable Schism, and yet take themselves for the most godly Christians. See his Preface to his second Treatise against the Donatist's of <hi>England</hi> (for so he calls the Separatist'.)</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you see what sence your own Leaders pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess, concerning this first Objection, which is fondly suffer'd to retain you from our Publick Assemblies. It is, certainly, a very Antichristian temper, and hath in it a very high Degree of Phanaticism, to censure Men for their Obedience to the Laws of God and the King. I'me sure it's contrary to an Apostolical Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, <note place="margin">Rom. 14. 3.</note>
               <hi>for him that eateth not, to Judg him that eateth: As well as for him that eateth, to Judg him that eateth not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I but</hi> (still Object our Lay-Separatists) <hi>The case is now much altered, by the many corrupt Impositions, and therefore we cannot Communicate with your Parochial Assemblies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I answer. The moderate <hi>Nonconformists</hi> themselves do (as they cannot, indeed, in Reason, do otherwise) with one consent declare, that Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from the Publick Worship of God, when it is meerly upon the account of some Corruptions and Defects in the Circumstantial Modes of Administrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, where the Substance of Religion is sound and good (maintaining neither Heresy in Doctrine, nor Idolatry in Worship) is to be absolutely condemned. But the Parish Churches of <hi>England,</hi> where the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of Religion is sound and good, are (confessedly) true Churches of Christ: <hi>Erg:</hi> They are not to be sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:66320:6"/> from, upon this pretence, that there are some supposed Corruptions and Defects in the Circumstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Modes of Administration. Where the Ground is sound and good, we may safely venture to raise our Building, the Quagmires should be round about us. <q>Shall men (<hi>says Mr. Ben. Bruning, in his Sermon preach'd at Ipswitch, at the Election of Parliament Men,</hi> 1660) chop off the Head of Religion it self, only because they find a Bauble upon its Sleeve? Nothing can justify Separation from the Church, but that Churches Apostacy into down right Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try or some Damnable Heresie. By all that I can learn from my Bible, we can be assured of nothing else: for Persons willingly to separate and refuse Communion with a Church, so long as God vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safe's Communion; how can this be justifyed, or how will it be answered? I know not. Those Words<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6. 17.</note>
                  <hi>come out from among them, and be ye separate,</hi> have been much abused for the encouragement of Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the Publick Assemblies of <hi>England.</hi> For who is it, but such as are forlornly void of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Charity, that dare say concerning the hundred Years past, that the Assemblies of the Church of <hi>England</hi> have had nothing of the Lord's gracious presence with them? Or that Ordinances have been empty things? He that affirms this, bears false wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness against thousands of glorifyed Saints in Heaven, and Gracious Souls on Earth, who have found to their everlasting comfort the Presence of God in his Ordinances among us. Suppose there are Miscar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages in the Management of God's Worship and Ordinances amongst us, yet if they be not such as drive God away, I see no reason they have to drive us away. If the Lord had ever intended to send any going whilst he afforded his own presence,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:66320:7"/>
[<hi>some] from among them</hi> would be improper Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage in such a case; It must have been [<hi>go] from among them,</hi> not <hi>come.</hi> Suppose our Lot be cast in a Church that hath Corruptions and Miscarrages whilst it holds the Substantials of true Doctrine and Worship; do any think in this Case, they cannot hold Communion with such a Church without being accessory to its Miscarriages, and incurring the guilt of its Corruptions? I must profess I am clearly of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Opinion and Judgment, and am confirmed in it from the Practice of our Lord and Master: Who was a member of the <hi>Jewish</hi> Church, whilst it was corrupt in Doctrine, Worship and Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation. 'Tis true, he was far from owning its Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions: He lamented and reproved them, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured a Redress; but still held Communion with it as a Member of it. He sharply reproves the <hi>seven Churches</hi> for what was amiss; and severely threatens them, if they amend not. But all this while, there is not the least blame laid upon any Member of those Churches, for not withdrawing or suspending their Communion. Did their Communion with <hi>the Church of Sardis</hi> make them accessory to the defilements of it? How then could our Saviour have truly said of them, that they <hi>had not defiled their Garments?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 3, 4.</note> Would any man take it well to have a Plague-mark clapt upon his Door because of some Uncleanness in his House? This is the usage that Christ meets with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, when any separate from a Church as Antichristi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an upon any Grounds short of gross Apostacy. Let all the World see that Principles of Loyalty, Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Civil Order, are no Inconsistencies with the most attainable heigth's of Heavenly-minded Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:66320:7"/>
            <p>These are the very Words of this excellent Man; which let any Separatists impartially consider, and then tell me, if impos'd Corruptions in a true Church, be sufficient to excuse their Separation from it.</p>
            <p>But the Question is, what are Corruptions and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions in the Worship of God. Suppose an hot headed Man, who in the late times of Rebellion and Confusion took upon him the Liberty to call such and such things Corruptions; doth this warrant them to be truly such?</p>
            <p>Let us consider what the more cool and tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Writers before the Wars called corrupt Impositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr. Byfeild, in his Commentary upon St.</hi> Peter, and<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 13.</note> particularly upon this Text, <hi>Submit to every Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Man for the Lords sake,</hi> saith; <q>That in Church Matters, the Magistrate may command, and the Subject must obey. And he sets down a Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of many things called <hi>Inventions of Man,</hi>
               </q> used in the Worship of God, without any Commandment of God, both before the Law, under the Law, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Law, that might lawfully be used. <q>Nay (saith he) Inconvenient Ceremonies in the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of God may be used, to prevent worse Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies. And then he goes on mentioning the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars,</q>
               <hi>Page</hi> 435. <q>In Ceremonial and Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantial things, it is not always a Sin to swerve from Examples in Scripture. It does not follow that if Christ did sit at the Supper, therefore it's unlawful to kneel. Sitting at the Sacrament was manifestly a Humane Invention; which shews that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of God about Circumstantial things might in some cases be transgressed without Sin, and were never intended to bind the Conscience abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:66320:8"/> as Moral Precepts in Substantials did. As for Example. The Command of God was that every Man-Child should be Circumcised the eighth Day; Yet the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> were not Circumcised in the <hi>Wilderness</hi> for fourty years together, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nay, (saith he) some significant Ceremonies were law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful: As the Altar by <hi>Jordan,</hi> the Cup at the Passo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, the covering on the Heads of Women, and the Love Feast, with the Holy Kiss. Read the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, and you will receive more Satisfaction.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr. Sprint,</hi> the Eminent old <hi>Conformist,</hi> who wrote that learned and Pious Book called the <hi>Necessity of Conformity in Case of Deprivation,</hi> will likewise suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently satisfy any unprejudic'd Reader, who is willing to read the Arguments on both sides.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr. Perkins,</hi> likewise, <hi>in his Exposition upon the Epistle of Jude,</hi> hath this passage. <q>If (says he) the Church err in matter of Religion, then must we consider whether the error be in a more weighty and substantial Point, or in matter of less impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. If it be in smaller points, (the Foundation being kept) we may not separate our selves. If it be in Substance of Doctrine, or in the Foundation, then we must consider whether it err of Humane Frailty, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or of Obstinacy: If of Frailty, we may not separate. The <hi>Church of Galatia</hi> was through Frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty quickly turned to another Gospel, and erred in the Foundation, holding Justification by Works; yet <hi>Paul</hi> writeth unto it as unto a <hi>Church of God.</hi> So likewise the <hi>Church of Corinth</hi> erred grievously, and overthrew the <hi>Article of the Resurrection;</hi> and yet <hi>Paul</hi> behaved himself accordingly unto it. But if the Church err in the Substance of Religion obsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately, then with good Conscience Separation may be made. Whence we see (as he afterwards con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes)
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:66320:8"/> that no man may with good Conscience separate himself from the Church of <hi>England;</hi> seeing it teacheth, believeth, and obeyeth the Doctrine of the Prophets and Apostles.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The Reverend <hi>Mr. Gurnal,</hi> in his Book called <hi>the Christian in compleat Armour,</hi> doth exceedingly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the scrupulous Separatists, who turn their Backs upon the Publick Worship of God, because of some faults in the Administration. <q>We find, indeed, saith he, Formality forbidden, but not Forms of Prayer: And we are commanded to <hi>beware of the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of the Pharisees,</hi> but we are not forbidden to hear their Doctrine.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr. Hudson,</hi> in his <hi>Vindication of the Essence and Ʋnity of the Catholick Church,</hi> greatly Laments Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the Publick Assemblies; and condemns those, who call their own Mother Whore, by name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our <hi>Church, Babylon, Egypt, Rome,</hi> &amp;c. That they may scum the Cream off our Assemblies, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vision, saith he, is the Devil's Musick, that which makes him laugh, should make us weep.</p>
            <p>This Passage of <hi>Mr. Gataker</hi>'s, is likewise very ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servable, that it's the Work of Angels, not men; at the end of the World, not now, to gather out of Christ's Kingdom all things that offend.</p>
            <p>By what then hath been alledged, this Argument for Separation must necessarily fall to the Ground: And tho there were really those Corruptions which the Dissenters do pretend (as I'me sure there is not) in the Publick Worship of our Parochial Assemblies; yet since all are satisfyed that the Substance of it is found and good, no man can, with a good Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, actuated by Christian Principles, absent him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self upon that account.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Well then</hi> (replyes the Separatist) <hi>I would go to</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>3</label>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:66320:9"/>
               <hi>the Publick Assemblies if I were left to my own Liberty of Conscience, but I cannot do it being compelled by Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and so imposed upon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why did you not do it then, when you were left <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>
               </label> to your liberty by <hi>Indulgence?</hi> What Compulsion absented you, when his Majesty granted you Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Conscience? Then you would not come, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause Authority did not compell you to it; and now you refuse, because it does. What a strange, irratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal way is this, of humouring your Arguments? What a querulous unchristian temper does such an Objection discover? I'm sure it would be judged a surly temper, and an high Act of Disobedience in any of your own Children, to tell you, he will not do such or such a thing because you impose your Commands, and require him to do it, and do not leave him to his own Liberty. But (to convince you fairly of this) pray consider the force of this plain Argument seriously with your selves, <hi>viz.</hi> Whatever is commanded by the Government, under which we live, and is no Sin against the Soveraignty of Almighty God, is a Christian's Duty. But to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the Publick Worship of God, is commanded by the Government under which we live, and is no Sin against Almighty God. <hi>Erg.</hi> It is an indispensable undoubted Duty.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Major</hi> Proposition in this Argument is plain from Scripture, <hi>Rom. 13. 1 Tit. 3, 1. 1 Pet.</hi> 2. 13. The <hi>Minor</hi> consists of two parts. First, the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment requires it, and secondly, It's no Sin against God. The first part is proved by the Law of the Land: The second is proved by the subsequent Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments.</p>
            <p>That which satisfyeth the Government under which we live, being sin, is a Subject's Duty. But
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:66320:9"/> such Attendance upon Publick Worship suits and sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfies the Government. <hi>Erg.</hi> It's our Duty.</p>
            <p>For if we ought to <hi>Pray for Magistrates</hi> that <hi>we may</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2. 1, 2.</note>
               <hi>lead a quiet and peaceable Life under them,</hi> it's no less our duty to do all lawful actions in order to the same end.</p>
            <p>If it be our duty to <hi>follow Peace with all men,</hi> the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate<note place="margin">Heb. 12. 14.</note> is undoubtedly comprehended, and may justly claim a Preheminence. If it be our Duty <hi>to serve all</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5. 13.</note>
               <hi>Men</hi> in all lawful and honest things, why must the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate be excluded? Shall places of Power be shut out of this common Priviledge? The great example of our blessed Saviour would hereby be thwarted, who conformed to an Humane Edict, because the Power commanded, and least he should give offence.</p>
            <p>And St. <hi>Paul became all things to all men;</hi> and we<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 22.</note> have an Apostolical Canon for Obedience which we ought to follow, if we profess our selves Christians.</p>
            <p>Men must not imagine they can free themselves from Subjection to lawful Authority by wrested Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and perverse Applications of Holy Scripture; as one lately, who told his Minister, That <hi>Christ had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to stand fast in the Liberty wherewith he had made him free.</hi> It's very frequent to hear Christians called upon to <hi>come out of</hi> Babylon, who were never in it; and to apply those Scriptures which call upon men to come out from amongst Idolaters and Heathens, as if spoken to Christians to separate from Religious Assemblies, because (perhaps) of some Corruptions. For shame let us not cry out against <hi>Papists</hi> for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Scriptures a Nose of Wax, and do the same our selves.</p>
            <p>Some Men (saith Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>) who Plead for Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Conscience, deny'd his Majesty (the late Royal Martyr) the use of His own Chaplains, and of the Form prescribed in the Liturgy.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:66320:10"/>
            <p>Do but consider the Judgments of your own Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers about this matter; and you shall find most of them agreeing in this, That the Imposition of things (not oppugning the Divine Law) by Lawful Authority, ought rather to be an Argument for Obedience, than against it. And this is acknowledg'd by divers <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformists,</hi> at the very <hi>Savoy-Conference;</hi>
               <q>That an Inconvenient Mode of Worship may be a Sin in the Imposer and in the Chooser and Voluntary User, who may offer God better and will not. And yet it may be, not only Lawful, but a Duty to him, who is necessitated to offer up that or none.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, The <hi>Independents</hi> themselves acknowledge, That a Man is obliged in Conscience to hold Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion but with the Purest Church they can.</p>
            <p>Now, if our Constitutions are such, that the <hi>Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chial Assemblies</hi> are the Purest Church we are permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to hold Communion with, then we ought to hold Communion with them by their own Argument, or else to go into other Countries where we may enjoy our Liberty in this Particular without breaking the Laws or disturbing the Publick Peace.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Knewstubs</hi> (the old <hi>Nonconformist</hi>) had so great a Reverence for the Laws, That he tells his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in his <hi>Epistle before his Sermons,</hi>
               <q>That he would not have his Book keep them at home to read on the Lord's Days, but would have them attend the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Worship of God notwithstanding.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And Mr. <hi>Sheffield,</hi> in <hi>his Discourse of Excuses,</hi> saith, <q>It may be lawful to read a good Book at home on a Sabbath Day; but if nothing hinder, it is both scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous and sinful to forbeast coming to the Publick Worship of God. Christian Liberty free's us not from Subjection to the Laws of God, nor from obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Laws of Humane Authority.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:66320:10"/>
            <p>The Laws made to compel men to attend the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Worship of God, were excellently designed in their Original and Piously intended. Men ought to prefer a Publick Good before a Private Humour. For (as is well observ'd in Mr. <hi>Duty's Epistolatory Discourses</hi>) <q>It would lay the Foundation for Strifes and Divisions in a Kingdom to have two ways of Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. It may agree with <hi>Machiavillian,</hi> but with no Christian Policy. Therefore to keep Unity intire, the Few must yield to the Major Votes.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>There's no man in his right reason (says a Reverend Nonconforming Divine) but will say there is a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity of Government, and if of a Government, then of <hi>Ʋniformity;</hi> for Schism in the Church threatens Ruine in the State. The Scepter can never be carried steddy, where the Winds of contrary Doctrines blow.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Stronge,</hi> in his Sermons called, <hi>Two Sticks made one,</hi> saith, that <q>The way to Peace and Unity is for men to condescend and yield to Government as far as they lawfully can, even against their own Rights.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus, Instead of murmuring against <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron,</hi> every Wise and Good man thinks it his Duty to give <hi>Thanks for Kings, and for all that are in Authority,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2. 1.</note> that God does incline their Hearts to make Laws to compel men to attend his Publick Worship. True Loyalty being a part of their Religion, they had rather the Civil Magistrate should drive them out of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate <hi>Conventicle</hi> into the Publick Assemblies, than out of the Publick Assembly, into the Private <hi>Conventicles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But we have now more Light than formerly, and the</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>4</label>
               <hi>Case</hi> (say they) <hi>is altered upon that account.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Suppose we have; if the light we pretend to be <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ans. </seg>
               </label> Darkness, How great is that Darkness? If our too much Light hath so scattered our sight (as Mr. <hi>Reynor</hi> in his <hi>Apology for Learning,</hi> notably observes) <q>That we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:66320:11"/> see our Duty, we have more cause to mourn than to boast. If we are struck blind with Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and become not able to see for Visions, let us beg pity rather than slight Counsel.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Read Mr. <hi>Edwards's</hi> Epistle to <hi>his Gangrena,</hi> and he tells you what effects our greater Light hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <q>Our Reformation hath produced De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation. The Parliament put down <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> and the Sectaries Cry down the <hi>Scriptures.</hi> They laid aside the Cross in Baptism, and these Baptism it self. The one pulled down the Picture of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and the other deny the Doctrine of it. The former were against Pluralities, and the others against Ministers Maintenance.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And Mr. <hi>Case,</hi> in <hi>his Sermon before the</hi> Parliament, tells the World, <q>That the Errors in the Bishop's days were but <hi>Tolerabiles Ineptiae</hi> compared with the <hi>Doctrines of Devils,</hi> taught afterwards.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And, in the <hi>Epistle to Mr.</hi> Pool'<hi>s Book against</hi> Beedle, we are told, That <q>Errors formerly walked in the dark, but now they appeared (<hi>Cum Privilegio</hi>) at Noon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day; such is the effect of our new and clearer Light.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in <hi>The Defence of his Cure,</hi> &amp;c. tells us, <q>That the old <hi>Nonconformists</hi> were neither Blind nor Temporizers. They saw the danger on both sides as well as we. Our Light is not clearer but less than theirs. We see not further into that Cause than they did. Change of time doth not change the Truth, nor will warrant us to change our Religion unless we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solve to change as often as the Times change. If we read over the Old <hi>Nonconformists</hi> Books against Separation, we shall find the same Objections answer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Then judge whether their Case and our's was not the same. Indeed the Case of Ministers Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity is much altered by a new Act, which requires
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:66320:11"/> subscribing new things; but that part of the Liturgy, which the People are to joyn in, is made better and easier, it being amended by change of the Transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and by some things explained, and some longer Prayers. And thirty years ago there were many bare Reading, no Preaching Ministers for one that there is now. Therefore our Case of Separation being the same with what it was of Old, it pities me to hear many say, we are grown wiser now, and have more Light than they; whereas our Writings shew upon the same Subject, that we are far below them. The World knows that the Turn of the Times put most of us into the sudden possession of our Opinions with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out one half of the Study which <hi>Ames, Cartwright, Parker,</hi> and others bestowed upon these Points. As for them that say, If Mr. <hi>Dod, Hildersham,</hi> and <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> were now alive, they would have been of their Minds, I desire them to prove it, or not affirm it. Did the Old <hi>Nonconformists</hi> want Light and Heat that could burn at a Stake for their Religion? Thus closely to the Point is Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And Mr. <hi>Calamy,</hi> likewise, expostulating with Mr. <hi>Burton</hi> the <hi>Independent;</hi>
               <q>Desires to know of him, Whether the old <hi>Nonconformists</hi> did not understand the Pattern of God's House as well as he; and yet they were against Separation.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Paul Baines</hi> denied, before the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil,</hi> his keeping any <hi>Conventicle.</hi> And told them. <q>It was only some Private Christians came one Day to his House to be resolved in a Case of <hi>Conscience.</hi> See his Life.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> (on <hi>the Canticles</hi> pag. 44.) observes, <q>That it's no Impeachment to Christian Liberty to submit to Christian Laws. It's Rebellion makes men say, <hi>Let us break their Bands in sunder, and cast away</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al. 2, 3.</note>
                  <hi>their Cords from us.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:66320:12"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Ball,</hi> I imagine, may charitably be suppos'd to have had the Spirit of God in as great a measure as any of our Dissenters; yet he declares that <q>He did not approve of the Practice of our Modern <hi>Independents,</hi> who at one Jump, leap'd both out of the Surplice and out of the Publick Assemblies also. See Mr. <hi>Newco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men's Irenicum, in the Preface.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Greenham</hi> (as you may read in <hi>his Life</hi>) made it his Business to do good and to prevent Schisms, to perswade to Peaceableness and Obedience; and told Dr. <hi>Burges,</hi> that <q>He durst not Discourage any from attending upon the Publick Worship of God to avoid the Ceremonies.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Dod, on the Commandements,</hi> persuades People to come to Church at the beginning of the Publick Prayers, performed by the Liturgy; <q>And not the Husband come when the Prayers are half ended, and the Wife when the Prayers are quite ended. And</q> he advised his own Daughter to take the Sacrament kneeling. As may be seen in the Epistle to <hi>Bishop</hi> Morton'<hi>s Book of Episcopacy,</hi> written by Sir <hi>Henry Telverton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But not to give you one Passage for all (further to convince you, that it is not strength of Grace, but Weakness, which is now the Cause of Separation) take this Remarkable one of Mr. <hi>Baxter's,</hi> which he himself gives you, in <hi>his Character of a weak Christian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>It's certainly (says he) a sign of a Weak Infirm Christian, who is not arrived to a confirmed State of Grace, to cause Discord and Divisions in the Church, and to run into unwarrantable Separations upon eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Modal Imperfection; and because his Charity is small he is apt to censure the strong Christian who hath more experience, and to think him unworthy his Communion. He is apt to be unreasonably con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:66320:12"/> of his own Apprehensions, as if all his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions were certain truth, and thinks all men Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant or Ungodly that differ from him, because he hath not impartially and thorowly studied all that may be said on the other side. The Authority of his chosen Teacher of Sect is greater with him than the Authority of all the Wise and Holy Persons in the World beside. If Discipline be neglected, if God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness be not promoted, and Prophaneness be not dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, the weak Christian thinks such a Church to be no Church. God hath taught him by Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to see the mischiefs of ungodliness, but he wants experience to know the Mischiefs of Church-Divisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. He knows the Evil of Sin, but not the Evil of Schism. Sometimes the Weak Christian will be Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox overmuch, and then none will be fit for his Communion that be not of his Opinions in Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted Droctrinals; such as <hi>Predestination, Free-will, The Manner of the Work of Grace, Perseverance,</hi> and such like. Sometimes the Weak Christian will be Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstitious over-much, and then none are fit for his Communion that Worship not God in the Method for Circumstantials that he judgeth best; and oftentimes by his peevishness and ignorance he proves a greater hinderance to the Churches Unity, than the Enemies to the Church▪ themselves. He doth not love those healing Books and Sermons, which narrow Differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces▪ and tend to Reconcile; but rather such as call aloud for Zeal for this or that controverted Point of Doctrine, or against some Circumstance of Worship or Discipline; and censureth many a Wiser Christian than himself, for many a supposed Sin, which is no Sin, but a Duty. If he hears a hard Name against any <hi>Opinion</hi> or <hi>Way</hi> of Worship, he presently takes a Prejudice against it; which prevails more with him
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:66320:13"/> than Reason could have done. If a Zealous Preacher do but call an <hi>Opinion</hi> or <hi>Practice Antichristian,</hi> it's a more effectual terror, than clearer proof. In the <hi>Litigious</hi> Titles of <hi>Pretenders to Supremacy,</hi> he is too hasty to interess himself in their <hi>Contentions,</hi> when the Controversie is only amongst States-Men and Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, and belongs not to <hi>Religion,</hi> yet the Odium shall be cast upon Christianity and Piety.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>The Weak Christian having too little <hi>Pat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nce</hi> and too much Passion is easily tempted to break his Bounds, and like <hi>Peter</hi> to run to his Unauthorized<note place="margin">Mat. 26. 51, &amp; 52.</note>
                  <hi>Sword,</hi> when he should submit to Suffering: So that he is apt to think that lawful which may be necessary to his Preservation; and presently thinks the Church is falling, when Humane Power is turned against it; and therefore with <hi>Ʋzzah</hi> he must put forth his hand to save the Ark, though it cost him his Life.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now I cannot imagine (from what this Reverend Man hath here said) How Men, of this Crazy Consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of Soul and low Stature in Christianity, can pretend to greater Light and more clear Discoveries; as if they were gotten into the Upper Form in the School of Christ, when they know not enough to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover their own Ignorance. So that by this Character of a Weak Christian we may judge of the Vanity of this Objection, in pleading for Separation more now than formerly upon pretence of more Experience, Knowledge, or Light. Such as think they have more Light, let them more diligently make use of it to see their Mistakes, and avoid them by it; and endeavour to <hi>walk as Children of</hi> that <hi>Light,</hi> which serves principally<note place="margin">Eph. 5. 8.</note> for this very end, <hi>to guide our Feet into the Way of Peace.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 1. 79.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Another Objection, here of late, made use of to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse Separation from the Publick Worship of God in our Parish Assemblies, is this.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:66320:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>If</hi> (say they) <hi>we should now join in Communion with</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>5</label>
               <hi>the Church of</hi> England, <hi>we should seem guilty of</hi> Apostacy, <hi>in building up the things we our selves once destroyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Objection this, how contrary to the Opinion <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>
               </label> and Practice of many of your own Teachers, I leave you to judge from the serious perusal of the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Instances. Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in his <hi>Defence of his Cure,</hi> &amp;c. hath this passage.</p>
            <p>
               <q>It is not (saith he) here convenient to inquire who hath destroyed Reformation, tho' it be easy to discern it. But this is certain, God hath set up the Government, that is over us, and our Governours take down, by their Laws, that which perhaps we accounted Reformation. This is not our Work, but theirs: They permit us not otherwise publickly to Worship God. And a Man in Goal doth ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly joyn in no Publick Worship at all: And where Men are in forbidden Assemblies, the fears of some, the passionate Discontents of others, and the distur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance by Soldiers, and Officers do take off much of the Edification, and hinder us from such a frame of Mind as is mnst desirable. To Worship God no where, is to go farther from Reformation, than to Worship him by the Liturgie. To do it of choice is one thing, and to do it as a Duty put upon us by God's Providence, and our Governours is another. It is God that hath pulled down our Liberty to serve him otherwise, and we must obey him. It's no faulty Mutability to change our Practice, when God by changing our Condition doth change our Duty; no more than it was in Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> who <hi>to the Jews became a Jew,</hi> and <hi>Circumcised Timothy,</hi> and shaved his Head, and <hi>became all things to all men.</hi> And no more than it was to St. <hi>Augustin,</hi> who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesseth that he would Worship God, as to Forms and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:66320:14"/> Ceremonies, according as the Church did with which he joyned wherever he came. It is sinful Pride and Tenderness of our own Honour that makes some men avoid their Duty, because those that are against them take occasion to reproach them, and call them <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states</hi> and Time-Servers. Can these Men suffer Death for their Religion, that cannot bear a little Reproach for it? We must not make such carnal Policies our Guide, as to forbear that which God doth make our Duty.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This is Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Sentiment of your Scruple, which his Practice seems to countenance as little; when writing his <hi>Retractions</hi> in these following Words, he declar'd how little he fear'd being branded with Apostacy, in doing what his Duty obliged him to.</p>
            <p>
               <q>I repent (saith he) of all that ever I said, wrote, or did since I was born, against the Peace of Church or State; against the King, His Person, or Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as Supream in himself, or as Derivative in any of his Officers, or any commissioned by him. I repent that I no more discouraged the Spirit of peevish quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling with Superiors, and Church-Orders; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther too much encouraged such, by speaking too sharply against those things which I thought to be Church-Corruptions. I repent that I did not more impartially consult with the best Lawyers that were against the Parliaments Cause—See his <hi>Admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to</hi> Bagshaw.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Bruning <hi>of</hi> Ipswich, in that (already quoted) <hi>Sermon</hi> of his, <hi>at the Election of Parliament Men in</hi> 1660, was so honest as to acknowledge <q>That the time past had been a time of exquisite Temptation; so that some that belonged to God, and were dear to him, had sadly miscarryed in the Simplicity of their hearts, by others more crafty than themselves.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:66320:14"/>
            <p>And Mr. <hi>Newcome,</hi> in that <hi>Loyal</hi> Sermon of his, called <hi>Ʋsurpation Defeated, and David Restored</hi> (preached by him on the publick Solemn Day of Thanksgiving, <hi>May</hi> 24. 1660. in the Collegiate Church of <hi>Manchester</hi>) thus reflected (and was never yet thought guilty of <hi>Apostacy</hi>) upon the late past Times and Actions: <q>Oh (says he) what Pretences of Religion and Godliness hath there been in the late <hi>Mischiefs,</hi> that have been perpetrated? Calling upon God; appealing unto God to decide the Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie, nay, perpetrating Villainy upon Impulses pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended from the Spirit of God, Security of Religion, Liberty for Tender Consciences, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This hath been cryed up, as their <hi>Good Old Cause,</hi> that had the Blood of <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Prophets</hi> at the bottom of it, like that <hi>Mic.</hi> 2. 10, 11. Nay, their Unheard of Villanies are made the fulfilling of their Vows: No return for their Deliverances and Victories so proper, as to raise our Foundations, <hi>Murther our King,</hi> pull down the <hi>Ministry,</hi> &amp;c. as no doubt it was in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign, yet all along to advance <hi>Religion</hi> too.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Humphreys</hi> did not think himself guilty of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stacy, when he wrote himself <hi>A Conforming Parishio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, tho he were a Nonconforming Minister.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's a good Observation of Mr. <hi>Wells</hi> in his <hi>Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Sabbatarian,</hi>
               <q>That the Sabbath is not duely sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied without our Attendance upon God's Publick Worship. <hi>Keeping the Sabbath,</hi> and <hi>reverencing the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary,</hi>
               </q> being inseparably conjoyned.</p>
            <p>You who are so afraid of Apostacy, as you call it, read the Story of <hi>Penry,</hi> the Separatist (in Mr. <hi>Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> against <hi>Williams, pag.</hi> 117.) executed in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Reign, who at the Place of Execution told the World, That he had grievously offended the Queens Majesty, and drawn away many of her Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:66320:15"/> Subjects into Separation, from the publick Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies; and, tho he did see his Error, and begged Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, yet, because he could not recal those whom he had led away, therefore he acknowledgeth, that their Blood might justly be required at his Hands.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Fox,</hi> who compiled <hi>The Book of Martyrs,</hi> did not think it Apostacy to complain of the factious tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent Spirits which had possess'd the rigid Separatists in his Time; and he saith, <q>They despised him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he would not rail against Bishops as they did: And therefore, he advised Governours to look narrowly after those Men, whose Hypocrisie was more pernicious than that of the Old Monks: For under a Pretence of greater Purity, they will never give over, until they have brought us under a <hi>Jewish</hi> Slavery—See his Letter in Dr. <hi>Fuller</hi>'s Church History, <hi>Lib. 9. p.</hi> 106.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Brown,</hi> from whom the <hi>Brownists</hi> first took their Name, did not think it <hi>Apostacy, and a building the things he once destroyed,</hi> for to renounce the Principles and Practice of Separation, and take a Parsonage cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Church. God in a strange and wise Providence so ordering it, that he, who had utterly renounced all Churches in <hi>England,</hi> as no Churches, should after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards accept of one Parish Church among them called a Church. Have not many amongst us, who cry out against Apostacy, Apostatized from their former Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and turned Independants; and so <hi>built the things they once destroyed,</hi> to comply with a politick In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest.</p>
            <p>Honest Mr. <hi>Parker,</hi> the Old Nonconformist, could say to the last (as may be seen in his Book, called, <hi>The prophane Schism of the</hi> Brownist, <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.) <q>It grieves me to think that I, who have written so much against the Separatists, should have the Dung of that Sect
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:66320:15"/> flung in my Face, which with all my Power I have resisted in the whole Course of my Ministry in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> And tho I think many of them fear God; yet I must apply our Lords Words to them, <hi>Father, forgiveM them, for they know not what they do.</hi>
               </q>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 23. 24.</note>
            </p>
            <p>To Conclude, did Dr. <hi>Reynolds</hi> Apostatize, when on his Death-Bed he desired to receive Absolution according to the Liturgy of the Church o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>England;</hi> and protest<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to Dr. <hi>Holland,</hi> that he did not argue before King <hi>James</hi> against the Ceremonies as things unlawful, but only as things Inconvenient?</p>
            <p>
               <q>Let us therefore follow rather that wholesome Counsel given us by <hi>Mr. Pagett</hi> in his <hi>Arrow against Separation,</hi> and endeavour <hi>to keep Faith and a good</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1. 19.</note>
                  <hi>Conscience,</hi> and not scare our selves and others, from Communion with the Church, with fears of Aposta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. Let us be affraid rather of falling from the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of God,</hi> by lapsing into Sin. And as for any Nick-named Apostacies let them go.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Well,</hi> But (says the Separatist) <hi>we have entered now</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>6</label>
               <hi>into a Solemn League and Covenant to endeavour greater Reformation in the Church, and therefore these good men's Arguments against Separation does not reach our Case.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But did one quarter of those that make this Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>
               </label> ever take the Covenant? And are you obliged to keep it, who never took it?</p>
            <p>But suppose you did take that Covenant: By what Authority did you make it? No man can bind him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self to that which is not in his Power. And an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful Oath is better broken than kept. Make a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant to Reform your own Lives and your own Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies if you please; and keep it when you have done, and you'll do well: But do not think your self en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to do your Governours Work.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:66320:16"/>
            <p>There's no Covenant can oblige a man to be so Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstitious, to Judge that to be Sinful which is Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful: Nor yet to be so Licentious, to Judge that to be Lawful which is Sinful. Wise-men think it as Glorious to become Martyrs for Peace, as Confessors for Truth: And will not suffer the pretence of Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to destroy Unity: But can Pray as heartily against Schisms as Heresies, notwithstanding any pretence to the contrary. Instead of making it a Question, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we may Lawfully hold Communion with the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish Assembly, the Question ought to be, Whether we may Lawfully Separate from the Publick Worship of God, because of some different Circumstantial Modes of Administration. And I would gladly, then know, whether ever any Man took a Covenant not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form his Understanding in that which is his apparent Duty. Doth the Obligations some Men have taken lay a Restraint upon Mens Judgments, so that they must not examine the Doctrines they hear from their Teachers? When they tell their People such and such Practices symbolize with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> may they not read such Discourses as shew <hi>how far</hi> England's <hi>symbolizing with the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>is just Ground for Separation?</hi> If others say kneeling is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful at the Sacrament, surely Men are not so tyed up by <hi>Covenant for Reformation</hi> as not to examine whether it be so or no, and to take all for Gospel which some Men deliver. The <hi>Bereans</hi> were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended<note place="margin">Acts. 17. 11.</note> for examining the Doctrines they were taught.</p>
            <p>My <hi>Lord Bacon,</hi> indeed, tells us of some, in his time, who looked upon it as a tempting of God to read or hear what may be said against their Opinion. I fear we have many such in our times; and at this rate Men may scruple until they come to their <hi>Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting Rest.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:66320:16"/>
            <p>But I would fain know what sort of Men among us have taken such a <hi>Covenant for Reformation,</hi> as not to hear and read what may be said against their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, as well as what may be said for them? And did not (I pray) they who took it oblige them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves not only against Sin but Schisme; and have they not broken the very Letter of it them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves?</p>
            <p>I'm sure <hi>Mr. Watson</hi> (in his <hi>Anatomy of man's Heart</hi> pag. 13.) told the Parliament that they had done so: And that Men act against God, when they act against that Order and Government which he hath set up in the World, and in the Church. <q>God hath (says he) set up Kings, Nobles and Judges in a Descent, and this makes up the Harmony; and these Powers are of God. Magistracy is the Hedge of a Nation, he that breaks the Hedg the Serpent will bite him. Here is just impeachment against the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Libertine who Pleads for Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science. Conscience! Must he have his Conscience, who hath sinned away his Conscience? Conscience must have a Rule; It binds only by Virtue of a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept. Get Conscience better informed: The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science of a Sinner is defiled, being defiled may err, and erring may suggest that which is Sinful: There is nothing can bind a Man to sin. Again, <hi>pag.</hi> 17. 'The Hypocrite (says he) is more Zealous against a Ceremony than against a known Sin: And have we not many in our Days Zealous against Popery? If they see a Cross, tho' in a Coat of Arms, they are much offended; but in the mean time, make no Conscience of other Sins. And (on the <hi>Beatitudes</hi>) O! how (says he) do Hereticks destroy the Truth of the Church by Error, and Schismaticks the Peace of it by Divisions! We have so many several Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:66320:17"/> God may justly unchurch us all, as he did <hi>Asta.</hi> The Sectary hath <hi>Sampson</hi>'s Foxes United to set the Church on fire.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>To hold Communion (saith <hi>Mr. Baxter,</hi> being a full Answer to this Objection in his <hi>Defence of his Cure,</hi> &amp;c.) in the Liturgy ordinarily, where we cannot have better; and extraordinarily where we cannot have better; and extraordinarily where we can have better, is a thing that we are bound to by the Covenant, and not at all bound against: And if there had been any word in it against Communion with the Churches that use the Liturgy, it had been Sin, and against our Duty, and therefore it could not bind. It is commonly agreed that if we vow a thing indifferent, it binds us not when the indifferency ceaseth; which may be by the Magistrates Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, or by another Man's Necessity, or by Change of Cases: else a man might before hand prevent most of the Magistrates Obligations, and his Parents, and Masters too, and escape Obedience, and then say with the Pharisee, it is <hi>Corban,</hi> or a devoted thing. We ought not to go to the Covenant to know what's our Duty in the Worship of God, but to the Scriptures, and if the Scripture make it not a Duty, the Magistrate's Law will make the doing of it a Sin; And if Scripture make it not a Sin, the Magistrates Command will make it a Duty. But when we know what is Duty or Sin, we may go to our Vowsnext, to prove that it is a double Duty, or an aggravated Sin, but not otherwise. The Covenant or Vow ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly binds us against Schisme, and the Renunciati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Communion is plain Schism. The Covenant binds us against all that's contrary to the <hi>Power of Godliness</hi> and sound Doctrine; but the Separation which I plead against, is certainly such. The Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant binds us to Unity and the nearest uniformity
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:66320:17"/> we can attain; but as the World goeth now, this Communion is the nearest, and needful to express our Unity. The Covenant binds us to <hi>Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> according to Gods Word, and the Example of the best Reformed Churches: But to prefer no Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Worship or a worse before the Liturgy, is De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation and Prophanation. It's greater Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation to prefer the Liturgy before none, than to prefer extemporary Publick Worship before the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy. All Reformed Churches in <hi>Chrystendom</hi> do commonly profess to hold Communion with the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish</hi> Churches in the Liturgy if they come amongst us where it is used. Therefore it seems to me to be Perjury and Covenant breaking, either to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer no Publick Worship before the Liturgy, or to refuse Communion with the Churches that use the Liturgy as a thing meerly on that account unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, see the same Author's rejoicing for his keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his own people from taking this <hi>Covenant,</hi> in his <hi>Farewel Sermon</hi> to them of <hi>Kidderminster,</hi> lately pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished. <hi>pag.</hi> 37.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr. Crofton,</hi> who was sent to the Tower for wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the Defence of the Covenant, yet, confessed <q>that he saw nothing in the Liturgy, but what, with a candid Interpretation, a good Christian might say <hi>Amen</hi> to.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Assembly of Divines,</hi> who framed the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant (and therefore best understood the extent of its Obligation) were against Separation, except five of them. And in their <hi>larger Catachism,</hi> they thought fit to prefix the <hi>Advice of the</hi> Scotish <hi>Divines.</hi>
               <q>That at Family Worship care ought to be taken that each Family meet by themselves, lest it tend to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of the Publick Ministry, and cause Schismes and Separations in the Church.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:66320:18"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr. Corbet,</hi> in his <hi>Plea for Lay Communion,</hi> tells the World, <q>That the Covenant or any engagement for Reformation can lay no Obligation to any thing that is not in our Power: And that it obligeth us against Separation and not to it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And now let any Separatist but seriously consider, what the Wisest-men of his own Party hath here told him, And he will sure be ashamed ever to urge his taking the Covenant as a sufficient Plea for his Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <p>But let such who insist so much upon a Covenant remember that they have taken a sacred Covenant to keep all Gods Commands; one of which is, to obey their Superiors both in Church and State: And their Salvation depends upon it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But</hi> (still objects, now-a-days, our Separatist) <hi>If I comply with the Liturgy at this Time, I should gratifie the</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>7</label> Papists, <hi>and weaken the</hi> Protestant <hi>Interest,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This is so far from being true, that the quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>
               </label> is true: For all the Arguments of <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ne'er did so much propagate Popery, as Division and Separation hath done. The Jesuites stand and clap their Hands to see the peevish Sectary stand out, and oppose the Government for Trifles.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Wood,</hi> Professor of Divinity at St. <hi>Andrews,</hi> writing against <hi>Lochier,</hi> tells the World, <q>That the separating Principle and Practice is like to prove of dangerous Consequence to the Church of God, a Disgrace to the Reformation, and will, in time, open a Door to Popery.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The Learned Mr. <hi>Gataker,</hi> in his <hi>Defence of</hi> Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shaw <hi>against</hi> Cann, saith plainly, <q>That the way to prevent Popery, is to abhor Separation from the Parochial Assemblies.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:66320:18"/>
            <p>That Excellent Preacher, Dr. <hi>Harris</hi> (a Man in great Reputation with our Dissenting Brethren, freely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, <q>That he conceived the way of gathering Churches into private places, to be very prejudicial to the publick Worship of God; and gave this Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to his Children, to carry themselves dutifully to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Authority; to see God in the Magistrate, and to look upon Order as a precious thing; and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be Authors, nor Fautors of any, either Faction, or Novelty. <hi>See his Life.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hildersham,</hi> in his Printed <hi>Letter about Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the Church of</hi> England, written to a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman who was sent to Prison, because she would not go to Church; he tells her, <q>That a private Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian may dislike the Corruptions that are in a Church; and may pray, and use all lawful means towards a Reformation; but he ought not to account all the Churches in a Nation as Heathens and Publicans, that is, such as with whom they may not lawfully communicate, and joyn in the publick Service of God. And Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> in his <hi>Epistle to Mr.</hi> Hilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sham's <hi>Letters upon</hi> John,</q> particularly mentions that Letter, and saith, <q>It hath so strongly and clearly convinced the Iniquity of that way of Separation, that I could not (saith he) but acknowledge in it, both the Wisdom of God, and the Weakness of the Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tist's Arguments, who, endeavouring to answer it, hath given himself, and his Cause such a deadly Wound in open View, as neither himself, nor all his Associates can be able to heal.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> Bates, <hi>in his Farewel Sermon,</hi> presses to Peace and Unity, upon the consideration of the great Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement the <hi>Romanists</hi> made of our Animosities and Divisions; they warming themselves at our Flames.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:66320:19"/>
            <p>
               <q>If ever Popery come into <hi>England,</hi> it must be at<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dr.</hi> Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>Bishop of</hi> Lincoln.</note> the Breaches made by Division and Separation (as a Learned Prelate of our Church observes) There is a Necessity of maintaining the present established Religion, in order to the prevention of Popery, whatever idle Men dream to the contrary. Read</q> the Discourse, called <hi>Foxes and Firebrands,</hi> and then let any man be of another Opinion if he can, and keep his Reason at the same time.</p>
            <p>The most Reverend Archbishop <hi>Ʋsher</hi> (as you may see in <hi>his Life</hi>) did, the last time he was in <hi>London,</hi> with great Thoughts of Heart, lament our woful Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visions and Separations, and the Animosities kindled amongst Christians upon the account of their several Opinions in matters of Religion. And observing how some opposed the Publick Ministry and Sacraments, and others spread Heresies and Blasphemy, he said, <q>He was confident the Enemy which had sowed these Tares up and down the Nation were Popish Agents, sent out of their Seminaries in sundry Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guises; which, if not supprest, would Issue in an Inundation of Popery, And accordingly that Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage is observable of <hi>Mounsier de l' Angle's</hi> (Minister of the Protestant Church at <hi>Roven</hi> in <hi>France</hi>) in his Book, written in the Year 1660, containing an excellent Charecter of his <hi>Majesty,</hi> the Present <hi>King of England</hi> (whom God long Preserve!) Thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding, by way of <hi>Letter to his Friend. Sir,</hi> This Prince is no such Person as the Jesuits report him. For his re-establishment is not a thing they hope for, but fear as a Thunderbolt; because they know, if he be once restored, he will rectifie those Disorders those Persons have fomented, who push on the Jesu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its Designs, and help them to fish in troubled Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as hitherto they have done.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:66320:19"/>
            <p>Nay, It hath constantly been the sence of many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sagacious and Wise Men, when once they saw <hi>Faction</hi> to grow bold and sturdy, greatly to fear, that the Protestant Interest would be sadly wounded by it; and they have, as it were by a Prophetick Spirit, told us to this Purpose; that if ever <hi>Popery</hi> did return in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Nation, it ought to be laid chiefly at the <hi>Schis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks</hi> door. And 'tis a <hi>Rule</hi> among the Jesuits them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, <hi>Dissensiones errantiumalet,</hi> &amp;c. That the Dissen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Contzen. Politic.</hi> l. 2. c. 19. §. 6.</note> among <hi>Protestants</hi> do serve the Interest of the <hi>Roman</hi> Cause. So that this very Objection which the Separatist here uses as an Argument for his Separation, doth fly back into his own face to Upbraid him for it, and persuade him strongly against it.</p>
            <p>Such (I'm confident) was Mr. <hi>Hildersham's</hi> Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; who was so far from thinking Communion with our Church an Encouragement to <hi>Papists</hi> in their Idolatry, that he himself (as some now living can witness) took the Sacrament kneeling. And an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former once swore, that he saw two of his Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion who did not Kneel, for which they were Fin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>: From whence it likewise appears, that himself and the rest did Kneel. So necessary do all good men (yea as even our Saviour himself did) think Union, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve the Peace and Purity of our Church. <hi>Every Kingdom divided against it self, is brought to Desolation and every City or House divided against it self, shall not stand.</hi> Mat, 12. 25.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But notwithstanding all this, I cannot</hi> (Objects f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>8</label> the Separatist) <hi>hold Communion with Railers and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutors; and such Scandalous Persons, as are most, both Ministers and People in the Publick Assemblies now.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Are not you one your self, whilst you say so of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers?<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>
               </label> I'm sure Dr. <hi>Manton</hi> in his <hi>Sermons on the 119th
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:66320:20"/> Psalm,</hi> much condemns this Antichristian Spirit, that prevails amongst <hi>Protestants,</hi> in censuring one another upon the account of different Apprehensions in lesser Matters, when they agree in the Foundation; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a great fault to cause Factions and Divisions in the Church, and then not indure to hear of it. And, as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> well observes, in his <hi>Cure of Church Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions,</hi> pag. 256. <q>Little do many Censorious Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists, who cry out against a Spirit of Persecution, think that the same Spirit is in themselves. For to think and speak evil of others is <hi>Persecution.</hi> And do not our Red-hot Sectaries do so, of truly Catholick and Sober Christians, who have more latitude than themselves? Calling them Carnal Gospellers, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Professors, and meer Moral men? Nay, it may be Time-servers, Turn-Coats, Apostates, and what not? Was it not <hi>Persecution,</hi> when the Separatists made such Work in <hi>Cromwel</hi>'s time? When so many were turned out of the Universities, and out of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry for not engageing? And out of the Magistracy and Corporations because they would not pray for success to their Wars, and give God thanks for their Victories, where the blood of thousands of confessed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Good men was shed?</q>
            </p>
            <p>But I pray tell me, what do you call Persecution? I doubt, if the Truth were known, you call Legal Prosecution, Persecution. If you break the Laws, and disturb the Civil Peace, must not the Penalty be exacted, but presently you cry out of <hi>Persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it may be you think Ministers are Persecutors and Railers, if they in their Pulpets condemn Faction in the State, and Schism in the Church. Let me tell you, if they should not do it, they were unfaithful to their Office. For never was there more need of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:66320:20"/>
               <hi>lifting up their Voices like a Trumpet to shew the People their Transgression,</hi> upon that account. For we have a Generation of men among us of <hi>Antimonarchial</hi> and <hi>Antiepiscopal</hi> Principles, who have declared their Sin as <hi>Sodom,</hi> and endeavoured if possible to blot out the very Name of <hi>Protestant</hi> from under Heaven: And like <hi>Jews,</hi> have made use of such barbarous means to keep out the <hi>Romans,</hi> which, if God does not won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully prevent, will infallibly bring them in. I'm confident that no Loyal <hi>English</hi> man, nor true <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Christian,</hi> will be prejudiced at his Minister, and say he's of a Persecuting Spirit, if he exposeth the Pragmatical Republican, and the Schismatical Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tist; <hi>That others may hear and fear, and do no more so wickedly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Wilson</hi> of <hi>Boston</hi> could tell his Hearers, that the Cause why God had brought such Dreadful Calamities upon that Country of <hi>New-England,</hi> was <hi>Choraism</hi> and <hi>Separation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter Sterry,</hi> the <hi>Independent,</hi> was not afraid to meddle with what, some thought, he had nothing to do with, when he told the little Parliament, <q>That God's Deliverance of the <hi>English</hi> Nation from Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Presbytery, was a greater Deliverance, than that of the <hi>Gun-powder Treason</hi> from the <hi>Roman</hi> Papacy.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hearle</hi> could discourse of the Independancy of <hi>Independant Churches</hi> upon Scripture, and it could be taken patiently.</p>
            <p>And Dr. <hi>Hill,</hi> at St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s, told them, that <q>
                  <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency</hi> was little better than <hi>Blasphemy,</hi> a Word not fit for Creatures, who are all Dependent upon God.</q>
            </p>
            <p>These Men's Hearers did not run away from them, and call them Tongue-Persecutors. Nay, I'm sure, should but the <hi>Nonconforming Ministers</hi> own words (in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:66320:21"/> these few Passages which are in these Papers, and in the many more which might, and have elsewhere been referr'd to) be repeated by any <hi>Conforming Divines,</hi> for their own Opinion, out of the Pulpet, they would presently be branded, with (what the first Broachers themselves must not yet be thought deserving of) the Name of Persecutor, Railor, and the like.</p>
            <p>But were our Ministers really such, as their Excla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations falsly represent; yet is even this no sufficient Plea for Separation.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Reiner</hi> of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> in his <hi>Resolution of that Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion, Whether Grace be essentially necessary to a Minister of the Gospel?</hi> Answers Negatively, and tells you, that <q>
                  <hi>Demas</hi> his Ministry was not to be rejected, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing he had forsaken St. <hi>Paul.</hi> And 1. He saith, God gives Ministerial Abillities to many men (such as Illumination, Utterance and Tongues) to whom he gives not saving Grace. 2. We have Examples of some such, who have been allowed Ministers, and Preachers of God's Word, who had Gifts, but no Grace, as <hi>Judas, Demas,</hi> and such who <hi>Preach Christ</hi> out of Envy and Strife, and the Scribes and Pharisees.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Perkins,</hi> in his <hi>Exposition upon Christ's Sermon on the Mount,</hi> says, <q>We may lawfully attend upon the Ministry of those men, whose Lives and Conversati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are Evil and Offensive, if their Doctrines be sound and Good. For the efficacy of the Word and Sacraments, administred by Man, is not from the Minister but from God. A Letter is not the worse because brought by a Dishonest Carrier.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Pemble,</hi> in his Discourse on the <hi>Nature and Properties of Grace.</hi> pag. 125. saith, <q>God sometimes makes use of the common gifts of Unregenerate Men for the good of the Church; as <hi>Solomon</hi> made use of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:66320:21"/> the <hi>Cananites</hi> and Strangers in the building of the Temple, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And Mr. <hi>Samuel Hieron,</hi> in his Treatise called, <hi>The</hi>
               <q>
                  <hi>Preachers Plea,</hi> saith, That A Minister's Life is no sufficient Argument against his Doctrine, or a just Plea for neglecting his Ministry. Put Case that all Preachers did confute their Sermons with their Evil Lives; and had <hi>Esau</hi>'s Hands with <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Voice; and were like a File, which smooths other things, yet it self remaining rough; this could not make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their Preaching. Is <hi>Physick</hi> and <hi>Law</hi> the worse, because some men are Lawless and Intemperate?</q>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Fenner,</hi> in his Sermon, called, <hi>Christ's Alarum to Drowsie Saints,</hi> says, <q>He dare not assert that God cannot make use of an Unregenerate Preacher to Convert Souls. Experience hath found this to be true. Some Godly Souls have confest this very thing, that such as now they find to be palpably Carnal, have been the Means of their Conversion. God may make the Crowing of a Cock a Means to awaken St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Conscience.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Anthony Burges</hi> in his <hi>Treatise of Faith and Assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> pag. 503. saith likewise, That <q>A Corrupt Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister may be used by God for Conversion of Souls.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> told <hi>Bagshaw,</hi> That he should not scruple to hold Communion with him notwithstanding he was a Railer, because the Apostle forbids only <hi>Civil</hi> eating, not <hi>Religious. 1 Cor.</hi> 5. 11.</p>
            <p>And is it not fit then, every <hi>English</hi> Man should submit rather to the Laws of his Country which are not contrary to the Laws of God? And are we not commanded to <hi>keep the King's Commandment, and that</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 8. 2.</note>
               <hi>in Regard of the Oath of God?</hi> Which is not (as Mr. <hi>Poole</hi> hath observ'd upon this Text, in his late <hi>English Annotations</hi>) <q>to be understood Universally, as if the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:66320:22"/> King should have commanded them to deny or Blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme God, or to Worship Idols, in which Case eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Christian man, who reads and believes the Bible, must needs confess that the <hi>Israelites</hi> especially were obliged to obey God rather than Man, but only of such Commands as are not contrary to the Will of God. Either 1. Because of that Oath which thou hast taken to keep all God's Laws, whereof this of Obedience to Superiors is one. Or 2. Because of that Covenant or Oath of Fealty and Allegiance whereby thou hast engaged thy self to him. Thus he.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Another Modern Objection that some Men make against Communion with the Publick Assemblies of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as by Law now established, is this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The way of Preaching is now quite altered, and the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>9</label>
               <hi>that are generally Preached are very corrupt; either meer Morality, or else thorow-paced</hi> Arminianism <hi>and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Doctrine of the Church of</hi> England.</p>
            <p>This Objection is vain and trifling, and never made <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>
               </label> but by Persons that never, I'm confident, understood either what <hi>Morality</hi> or <hi>Arminianism</hi> means.</p>
            <p>Our Blessed Saviour comprehends the <hi>Loving of God with all the Heart, Soul, and Strength,</hi> as the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of the Moral Law. And Wise and Good men, who have thorowly studied the <hi>Arminian</hi> Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies are inclin'd to think that the Difference is more in Words than Things; and a Man may be a very Pious Christian that practises the Sermon of a <hi>Calvinist,</hi> or an <hi>Arminian,</hi> because they agree, if not in their <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> yet in their <hi>Application.</hi> It is an easier thing to <hi>believe</hi> in <hi>Christ</hi> as our Saviour meant it, than to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand the <hi>Definition of Faith,</hi> as the <hi>Schools</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound it. Those Doctrins are most likely to be true, which most promote the Honour of the Creator and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:66320:22"/> the Diligence of the Creature. There are many Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culative Points controverted amongst Learned Men, of which a Man may believe either Proposition, and yet be a very good Christian. As for Instance. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose a Man believe the <hi>Predestinarian</hi> Doctrine, and that which moves him to it is, because he judgeth Free-grace best celebrated by believing it so irresista<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that to whomsoever it's intended, he will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be happy: Or, Suppose a Man questions those Doctirnes, if this be his Reason, because he thinks Divine Goodness most magnified by supposing it so Universal that it will make every man happy, if it be not his own fault.—See Mr. <hi>Boyle's Seraphick Love.</hi> pag. 104.</p>
            <p>He that believes the <hi>Apostle's Creed,</hi> and leads his Life answerable thereunto, need not doubt of accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with Almighty God through Jesus Christ. The World was never all of one mind, since there was but one Man in it; nor ever will be again, so long as there are two; especially in such Points which are not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary to Salvation. It's a very great fault, for men to charge the Doctrines they hear, with such odious Consequences which the Preacher never intended. Suppose a Minister Preach up the necessity of Personal Righteousness according to the Doctrine of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle. 1 John 3. 7. <hi>He that doth Righteousness is Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous;</hi> why must the Hearer run away and say that he denied the imputed Righteousness of Christ, when he only told them, that for men to depend upon the imputed Righteousness of Christ, without labouring to be inwardly and really Holy, could never save them? Must not a Minister condemn the <hi>Antinomian</hi> Doctrine, but presently all the Parish must be told, he's a Corrupt man; thereby rendring his Ministry in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effectual? I fear this is one of the Temptations of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:66320:23"/> the Devil, to steal away the Good Seed when it is sown.</p>
            <p>Do not all Ministers agree in that great Truth deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by our Saviour. <hi>viz. He that believeth shall be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark 16. 16.</note>
               <hi>and he that believeth not shall be damned?</hi> It may be you take their Doctrines to be different, meerly from a different way of expressing themselves: But I would know, whether by the same way of excepting against Ministers Doctrines as unsound, you may not also re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse to hear many <hi>Nonconformists;</hi> who are called <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minians, Free Willers,</hi> and I know not what; who have been abused by some of your selves, when their Discourses concerning <hi>Divine Praescience,</hi> &amp;c. have not been presently understood? Those are, certainly, the best Principles which regulate Mens Practices; and they are the best men, who live the best Lives, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute all that's Good to God, and all that's Evil to Man. Doth your Minister own the merit of Christ in the point of Justification, and the Spirit of Christ in the Work of Sanctification? Do not quarrel with his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine for you know not what, so long as he preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth up <hi>Practical Christianity.</hi> Exceeding true is that Saying of Dr. <hi>Bolton,</hi> in his <hi>Arraignment of Error,</hi> viz. That <hi>A Scrupulous Conscience is not always a sign of a Broken Heart, but sometimes of a Broken Head.</hi> Some men do not understand the Doctrine they hear, and then they condemn the Preacher as erronious. Be convinced that the great <hi>Design of Christianity</hi> is to make men good, and where it hath not that effect, it matters not much, what Church such a man is of; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause a Bad man can be saved in none. Therefore ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver cry out against Preaching up <hi>Morality,</hi> until you find People mend their Manners. If <hi>Ministers,</hi> after the Example of St. <hi>John Baptist,</hi> call upon their <hi>Hearers</hi> to endeavour to Reform their Hearts and Lives, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:66320:23"/> ignorant prejudicial Hearers cry out against them, that they Preach upon meer <hi>Morality.</hi> I pray read the Learned Sermons of several Eminent Episco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Divines, and you will find excellent Discourses upon the <hi>Creed</hi> as well as upon the <hi>Ten Commandments.</hi> I fear we may attribute very much of our present Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities to the Intricate Enthusiastick Comments of many men, who left the plain way of preaching Peace and Purity, and pretended great skill in unclasping the Sealed Book, and <hi>casting the Water</hi> of the seven Vials, upon whomsoever they were displeased with. Perhaps there are more good Preachers, than Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Hearers. We have many in <hi>England,</hi> who think every Husbandman qualifyed to Sow the Seed of the Word. And he that can tend Sheep, is abundantly furnished to have the oversight of God's Flock. Such Incompetent Judges are many People, of their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters Ability and Learning.</p>
            <p>But that this pretence of the Ministers Preaching <hi>Arminian</hi> Doctrine may appear but a vain Excuse, I pray consider: You have many Publick Preachers who never meddle with those Controversies in their Pulpits whatever their Judgments are: But they Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently keep to Scripture Language, and, as near as may be, to the Terms, in which the Articles of our Church are expressed, on purpose to prevent that Plea for Separation. I am very confident, who ever with an Honest Mind attends the Publick Prayers and Sermons once a Month for a Year together, will think it his Duty to do it every <hi>Sunday.</hi> His vain Pretences will then vanish, when he finds the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are so comprehensive, and the Sermons so Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal as generally they are.</p>
            <p>
               <q>The things Necessary to Salvation are (as one well observes) Plain and Few and Easie, not diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:66320:24"/> nor requiring much time to be Learned. As (1) for Men to profess the Holy Trinity, as the Object of Worship. (2) The Holy Scriptures, as the Rule of Worship. (3) A Place of Eternal Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sedness, as the Reward of Worship, and (4) the most Ancient and best Reformed Church, as the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test Example of Worship.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But</hi> (still goes on our Modern Separatist to Object) <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>10</label>
               <hi>that which, notwithstanding all this, makes me think Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating with your Church now more doubtful, is, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause our</hi> Nonconforming <hi>Ministers themselves will not go to Church, whereas formerly they did.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's very unreasonable to make the Practice of the <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>Nonconforming</hi> Ministers a Rule to the People. For it's well known, that one Reason why they are no more seen in the Publick Churches, is, because the Law permits them not to dwell within five Miles of a Corporation. So that while you are looking for them in our Publick Assemblies, they perhaps are retir'd into some obscure Country Village. They are in danger of being imprisoned, if they should be obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved there, unless they have taken the <hi>Oxford-Oath,</hi> which very few have done.</p>
            <p>Besides what signifieth another Man's Practice as a Rule to me? The Law of God and the Law of the Land ought to be my Rule, and no Particular Examples if they contradict that. But what if some Rigid <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformists</hi> will not come at our Publick Assemblies? Others that are more Moderate and Peaceable will do it, and do do it, especially in the Country, and before the Indulgence came forth: And they thought it their Duty to return to the Communion of the Church again, when that Liberty was prohibited by Authority. And so have many Private Christians, who think themselves bound in Conscience so to do.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:66320:24"/> If Men will follow Examples, they ought to imitate those, who are most Humble and Prudent, rather than those, who are most Hot and Violent.</p>
            <p>Hath not Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> in his <hi>Defence of his Care,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to the World, <q>That he himself goeth to his Parish-Church and takes the Sacrament Kneeling, on purpose to convince People that he doth not think it unlawful so to do? And hath not Mr. <hi>Sam. Clark,</hi>
               </q> in his own <hi>Life, written by himself,</hi> declared that, <q>Although he could not conform as a Minister in the Year 1660. Yet he durst not Separate from the Publick Assemblies, and gather a Church out of a Church, because he judged the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to be a True Church? And Mr. <hi>Pool</hi> in his</q>
               <hi>Vox Clamantis in Deserto,</hi> advised his <hi>Nonconforming</hi> Brethren, many Years ago, <q>To do all the good they could within the Compass of the Laws, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the Honest Conformists and strengthen their Hands.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And Mr. <hi>Ash</hi> observed, <q>That if Men deny to hold Communion with such a Church as our's is, (<hi>viz.</hi> The Church of <hi>England</hi>) there hath not been a Church in the World this thousand Years with which a Man might lawfully Communicate.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Gouge</hi> that excellent Man, <hi>who went about do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good,</hi> and constantly attended the Publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of God in the Parochial Assemblies, told his Friends, <q>He thought himself bound in Conscience so to do: And he also caused the Prayers of the Church to be translated into the <hi>Welch</hi> Language: See Dr. <hi>Tillotson's Sermon Preached at his Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But it is likewise</hi> (I observe) <hi>Objected by our Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senters,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>11</label>
               <hi>that if they should not still attend the Ministry of the</hi> Nonconforming <hi>Ministers, They must starve for
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:66320:25"/> want of Maintenance. They are Poor and Indigent, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving lost their Livings,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>A Private good, is not to be preferr'd before a <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>
               </label> Publick; and it is fitter for one man to Perish, than a whole Comonm-wealth. But however, it is evident they are not all so Poor, tho' they have lost their Livings; for many of them can subsist very comfortably without Preaching. And for those that are Poor, tho' the Laws oblige you not to hear them in numerous Auditories, yet they do not forbid your Charity. You may be as kind as you please to them and their Families. If, instead of setting up Separate Congregations, they had continued in Corporations, and not refused to take the <hi>Oxford-Oath,</hi> but by their Attendance upon the Publick Worship, and shewed a good Example to their former Hearers, had spent their time in Personal Conferencies and Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions from House to House (the Law allowing four, besides the Family) they had more promoted the Practice of Pieth and encouraged many conformable Persons to have been their Benefactors; by such a Prudent and Peaceable Carriage, which yet I hope is not to late too begin.</p>
            <p>Besides, for your Ministers to continue now their Preaching against Law, to procure a maintenance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst you, is by no Means justifyable, and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently upon that account, you ought not to hear and maintain them separating from the Church Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's true, the Apostle saith. <hi>He that provides not for his Family is worse than an Infidel:</hi> Yet the same A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle observes, that we ought <hi>not to do Evil, that good may come,</hi> because the <hi>Damnation</hi> of such <hi>is just.</hi> Now tho' it be a Duty to Preach the Gospel, yet it's not the Duty of all Men, at all Times, and in all Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:66320:25"/> At the first Plantation of Christianity, and Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing of the Gospel, the Apostles had an immediate Call from God, and by Virtue of that <hi>Patent</hi> under the <hi>Broad Seal</hi> of Heaven had Authority to obey God rather than Man: So that they might well say, <hi>Wo to us if we Preach not the Gospel.</hi> And certainly when the Conversion of Souls is the chief Motive, it would carry Men into the most Ignorant and Barbarous Parts of the World, to open mens Eyes and turn them from <hi>Darkness</hi> to <hi>Light,</hi> and from the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Satan</hi> unto <hi>God,</hi> as did the Apostles.</p>
            <p>The Old <hi>Nonconformists</hi> did all the good they could in a Private Capacity, when they were silenced by the Bishops from preaching Publickly. And they thought it their Duty to submit to their Suspensions, so long as their Diocesans did it by the Law of the Land: As Mr. <hi>Rathband</hi> observes <hi>in his grave Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions.</hi> (a Book written in the name of several of them.)</p>
            <p>And so Old <hi>Mr. Parker</hi> challenges the World to give an Instance, if they could, of any Unpeaceable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness or Obstinacy of any of them; or of any Signs of Pride or Contempt of Authority. <q>Do we (saith he) perswade any man to refuse the Ceremonies for which we suffer? Do we not stretch our Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences to the utmost to conform? We do not <hi>wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly</hi> cast off our Ministry: But we submit to the Providence of God who calls us from it. See his <hi>Book of the Cross.</hi> Part 2, pag. 34.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr. Geree in his Vindiciae Ecclesiae Anglicanae</hi> (the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign of which is to shew, that tho' there be need of <hi>Reformation</hi> in, yet not of <hi>Separation</hi> from the <hi>Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Christ</hi> in <hi>England</hi>) in the <hi>Epistle</hi> Dedicated to Learned Mr. <hi>Riohard Capel,</hi> he saith, <q>That for men to Preach Publickly against the Command of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:66320:26"/> without an immediate Call from God, is a thing which he never thought excusable from <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction:</hi> Nor likely to be long tolerated. And he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so makes this Observation, That of all the spiritual Converts that are in our Church, it may be truly affirmed, that not one of ten thousand hath been converted by a Separatist, whilst of that Opinion; They more minding the proselyting of the conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to their way, than the converting of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane to the way of Truth. And concludes, That the Cure of <hi>Separation</hi> would further <hi>Reformation,</hi> as much as <hi>Reformation</hi> weakens <hi>Separation.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Many of the <hi>Parliament Preachers,</hi> in the Late Times, we find frequently calling upon them to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press <hi>Divisions in Religion,</hi> by their Civil Authority; as being the Keepers of <hi>Both</hi> Tables: And they tell them, <q>The Omission of their Duty in that Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar would render them accessory thereunto. See Mr. <hi>Marshall's</hi> sermon and others.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Seaman</hi> tells the Parliament that the Power of Magistrates in Matters of Religion is now struck at. And, saith he, <q>Besides the Prophane and Scandalous Ministers, there are a new sort arisen amongst us, who thrust themselves into the Lord's Vineyard, and it's no less than Persecution (so they common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly give out (to Desire to have their Suspicious Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions examined, and <hi>they</hi> commanded to forbear Publishing them. See his <hi>Sermon</hi> called <hi>the President for Kings and Princes.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Thanks be to God, our Magistrates do not forbid the Preaching of the Gospel, nor the practisiing of that excellent Part of it, <hi>the relieving of the Indigent:</hi> They only restrain some particular Persons, whose Principles will not permit them to submit to the Publick Constitutions, from Preaching, but not from
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:66320:26"/> subsisting by your Benevolence. You may maintain them, I hope, without separating from Communion with us to hear them Preach, We having so many and so good Men of unspotted Lives, who Preach sound Doctrine, and are incouraged thereto by our Laws.</p>
            <p>But now the concluding Objection of all, which our Dissenters urge the most vehemently against their Communion with our Church, is this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There hath</hi> (say they) <hi>been so many Books written of</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>12</label>
               <hi>late in Defence of</hi> Nonconformity, <hi>that I cannot be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy'd; but still remain in Doubt, Whether it be lawful to hold Communion with the</hi> Parochial Assemblies: <hi>I vehemently suspect it to be sinful, and</hi> whatsoever is not of Faith is Sin, <hi>and therefore there's an end of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There's not an End of the Controversie for all that. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>
               </label> I pray examine first, whether you do not make use of this Plea merely for a pretence: And in order to your own Tryal, I'll refer you to one of your own admired Ministers, for Directions how you may know the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between Wilfulness and Tenderness of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science. It is Mr. <hi>Jer. Burroughs,</hi> in his <hi>Irenicum,</hi> pag. 36, &amp; 37. <q>If a man (says he) be proud and turbulent in his Carriage, and despise his Betters, and be apt to publish his mistakes, and not humbly and modest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conceal them; It's then a sign the Devil is in his Will, and not in his Conscience, when a man oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth the Judgments of many more Godly and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed than himself; and when he neglects the means of better Information, not studying what may be said against his Opinion as well as what may be said for it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The Reverend <hi>Mr. Bernard,</hi> in his <hi>Counsells of Peace,</hi> hath given excellent Rules in Case of a doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:66320:27"/> Conscience, and they are these very observable ones which follow. <q>Be sure to maintain and uphold all that is manifestly good in Church or State. If there be manifest Evils, Labour in your Place, by the best means to have them amended in a peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble way; and bear with lighter faults, for a time, until a fitter occasion be offered to redress them. As for likelyhoods of Evil, make them not apparent Evil by ill Interpretation, where neither the State intends it nor maintains it. Take doubtful things ever in the best part. Judiciously distinguish be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the abuse of a thing, and the use of it. Make a difference between Publick Establishments, and Personal Errors of some: Between Substance, and Circumstance: Between sound Doctrine, and bad Application. Again, never presume to Reform others until thou hast Reformed thy self. Do not disobey the evident Command of God, where there is nothing but probability of sinning in obeying the Precept of thy Governour. Do not set Opinion before Judgment. Set aside Fancy, and do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse to obey Authority, where it is not plain that you Sin against God in so doing. Be more afraid of offending a Lawful Magistrate, than many pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Persons. Where thou canst not yield, there humbly beg pardon: Where thou canst not be to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerated, be contented with Correction for safety of Conscience: It's not enough, to excuse Obedience, to say it seems to me to be a Sin. I pray how doth it appear to be so? Is it <hi>simply</hi> so? Shew me the <hi>Prohibition:</hi> Or is it <hi>Accidentally</hi> so? Only in the <hi>abuse</hi> of it, or through <hi>Ignorance</hi> of its Lawfulness? Or dost thou only <hi>Conjecture</hi> it to be so? Consider, none of these things can Discharge from the neglect of a known Duty, as Obedience to Authority is.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:66320:27"/>
            <p>The Rational and Excellently Learned Casuist, <hi>Bishop Sanderson,</hi> in his <hi>Sermon upon</hi> that Text, <hi>what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 14. 23.</note>
               <hi>is not of Faith is Sin,</hi> tells us to this purpose, that from hence some men take Occasion to tell us, that they cannot go against their own Conscience, for any Magistrates pleasure whatsoever. <q>Judg I pray you (saith he) what preverseness is this, when the Blessed Apostle commandeth us to <hi>Obey for Conscience</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 13. 5.</note>
                  <hi>sake,</hi> that Men should <hi>disobey,</hi> and that for <hi>Conscience sake</hi> too. Thou sayest, It is against thy Conscience. I say in the Case of doubtfulness, it is not against thy Conscience. For doubting properly is, when the Mind is held in suspence between two ways: Uncertain whether of both to take. And in this Case the weight of Authority should cast the Scale: A repugnant Conscience, I confess, is another thing. If the Conscience have already passed a Judgment upon a thing, and condemned it as simply Unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; In that case a man ought not to obey, although his Conscience hath pronounced a wrong Sentence; and erred in that Judgment: Yet he sins in disobey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Magistrate; from which Sin the following of the Judgment of his own Conscience cannot ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit him. Such is the Perplexity men cast them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves into by Error, Ignorance and Obstinacy, that they can neither go with their Consciences, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them, but they shall Sin. But you will yet say, It's safer to forbear in a doubtful Case; I say so too: Only let the Case be rightly stated. As for Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample: Suppose a man doubt whether it be Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to Kneel at the Communion, thou thinkest it sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for thee perhaps not to kneel. So should I too, If thou wert left meerly to thine own Liberty. But if Authority Command thee to kneel, which whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be Lawful for thee to do, or not, thou doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:66320:28"/> est; thou cannot chuse but thou must needs doubt also, whether thou mayest lawfully disobey or not. Now then here apply the Rule (of taking the safer way in a doubtful Case) and see what will come of it. Judg, since thou canst not but doubt in both Cases, whether it be not the safer of the two, to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey doubtingly, than to disobey doubtingly. Hold to the certainty, and let the uncertain go. It's cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, thou ought to obey the Magistrate in things not contrary to the Will of God; but whether the thing now commanded is contrary to the Will of God is uncertain to thee, because thou doubtest. Act safely, therefore, and obey.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And the Reverend Mr. <hi>Paul Baines</hi> tells us, in the Letter he wrote to his Friend to resolve the doubt concerning kneeling at the Sacrament. <q>If (says he) twenty Scruples should arise in my mind about it, I should yet believe the Gesture Lawful, for the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons before named, which you may see in his Book at large.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr. Baxter,</hi> likewise, very well observes in his <hi>Reasons for the Christian Religion</hi> that, <q>A tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science is as tender of being Guilty of Divisions, Schisme, and Separation, as of Drunkenness, Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or any other Enormous Sins.</q>
            </p>
            <p>So that you may, by this time I doubt not, see hence enough to convince you of the insufficiency of this mighty Objection to excuse your Separation from the Parochial Assemblies of our Church.</p>
            <p>Let not therefore the Pretence of greater Purity, destroy Unity; Nor the <hi>tything of Mint, Anise and Cummin,</hi> make us <hi>neglect the greater</hi> and more weighty <hi>Matters of the Law.</hi> Let us Labour after those Divine Qualifications which give the Essential Forme, and Genuine Complexion to Christianity, such as Love
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:66320:28"/> and Goodness, Truth and Mercy, Peace and Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness: And shun those malignant Epidemical Distem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers which wound the Vitals of Religion, such as An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Wrath, Clamour, Rebellion, Faction and Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And let us remember that all the parts of Instituted Worship, are but designed to bring the Mind and Manners of men into a nearer Correspon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with the Divine likeness; and more exact Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblance of that Pure and Holy Being who is the Object of our Worship: Vesture, Gesture, Time and Place, Forms of Devotion and Modes of Expression being but the Appendages of Religion, and therefore unbecoming wise and good Men to disturb the Peace of the Church about them, if they do not in all things suit with their private Humours. Let us wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly therefore (to conclude) observe the Apostles most excellent Directions. <hi>With all Lowlyness and Meekness,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephes. 4, 2. 3.</note>
               <hi>with long suffering forbearing one another in Love. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to keep the Ʋnity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>